Guide to the John E. Brennan Outdoor Advertising Survey Reports, 1947-1980 and undated RL.00148
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John E. Brennan Outdoor Advertising Survey Reports
1947-1980 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Brennan, John E.
RL.00148
47 Linear Feet
79,491 Items
Online Items
Selected items from this collection have been digitized and are available in: Resource of Outdoor Advertising Descriptions (ROAD) - Duke Digital Collections
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The John E. Brennan Outdoor Advertising Survey Reports were transferred to the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library from Fairleigh Dickinson University in 1996.
Thanks to Brennan's son, John P. Brennan, and nephew, Joe Callo, for providing background information for this collection.
Biographical Note
1906 John Edward (Jack) Brennan born to Mary Ellen (Nellie) Norton Brennan and Patrick Brennan in Hasting-on-Hudson, NY.
1945 Established outdoor advertising company, Standard Outdoor Advertising, Inc.
ca. 1947 or 1948 Established Poster Appraisal Service to provide research to the outdoor advertising industry on advertising design effectiveness.
1947-1970s Conducted outdoor advertising design surveys.
1948 Resigned as executive vice president of Standard Outdoor Advertising, Inc.
1940s-1950s Established Outdoor Advertising Research Institute as part of surveying activities.
ca. 1974 Retired from taking surveys.
1984 Died.
Little is known about the early years of Brennan's career although he may have worked for the Outdoor Advertising Association of America (OAAA), Outdoor Advertising Inc. (OAI), and/or General Outdoor Advertising Co. In the course of his survey work, he founded several companies including Poster Appraisal Service (PAS), the Outdoor Advertising Research Institute, and General Media and Copy Research Co. PAS appears consistently throughout the collection, but in some spots it is referred to as A Division of General Media and Copy Research Co. Brennan moved his family and his business back and forth between Florida, California, and New York. The companies were established by Brennan, but various family members worked with him such as his elder brother Thomas, his wife Ann, his sister Jo, as well as many contract workers.
Collection Overview
The John E. Brennan Outdoor Advertising Survey Reports document the professional endeavors of outdoor advertising design researcher John E. (Jack) Brennan for the time period 1947 to 1980. His work primarily consisted of conducting market surveys on the effectiveness of billboard advertisement design and layout, and reporting his findings to subscribers to advance design efficiency for the industry. About 786 surveys cover 15,720 different advertisement designs posted on signs in major markets around the US. Forty-two different cities were covered in 27 states. His survey interviewers questioned participants on how well they remembered advertisements and product brand names. Brennan then analyzed the survey data to produce practical information for advertisers and advertising companies on improving advertisement copy, thereby increasing advertising efficiency and profits. His emphasis was on outdoor advertisement design and copy, not traffic or other outdoor industry factors. The collection is comprised mainly of paper files, most containing color photographs attached to the paper data reports or sleeved along side them. Other significant items include the Copy Clues reports which capitalize on the data Brennan compiled, suggesting outdoor advertisement (also known as poster) design improvements. Other supporting materials within the collection include survey methodology information, related writings, summary data files, and business correspondence. Even without the context of Brennan's survey forms and data, the collection is a sizable photo library of mid-20th century commercial art created for outdoor advertising. Additional description of the individual series presented below may be found within the container list.
The collection begins with a small amount of Business Correspondence related to the surveys completed by Brennan's company Poster Appraisal Service (also General Media and Copy Research Co., and Outdoor Advertising Research Institute). Information documenting how Brennan conducted surveys makes up the next series called Methodology Files, which includes some interview forms and instructions. These are followed by the Outdoor Advertising Survey Reports themselves, which form the bulk of the collection. An individual survey was normally conducted in one city using about 20 different advertising designs. Each report is a compilation of data for one billboard advertisement, including a breakdown of statistics by male and female participants, and usually including color snapshot photographs of each design. Researchers of the collection can see the photos used in survey interviews, noticing how brand names were hidden and revealed as participants were questioned as to whether they remembered the entire advertisement and/or the brand name advertised. Design efficiency for individual cities may be studied since surveys are arranged by geographic location. Data may also be studied over time since ads are arranged chronologically within each location grouping. Certain ads were also compiled and survey data studied according to product type. For example, researchers may see how effective certain candy bar advertisements were across the country. Brennan encouraged subscribers to his service to look at reports themselves and come to their own conclusions about how to improve billboard advertisement design.
The Outdoor Advertising Survey Reports Series is also documentation of the more than 15,000 pieces of creative work produced by many different advertising agencies and their advertisers including D'Arcy Advertising; Foote, Cone, and Belding; J. Walter Thompson; McCann-Erickson; and Young and Rubicam. The photographed billboards were operated by many outdoor advertising companies including Central, Foster and Kleiser, Houston Poster, Middleton, Packer, and United. In addition to the photos with the survey reports, there are also several files of loose photographs, including pictures of billboards that were likely produced in preparation for surveys. A sampling of the product brands featured in the advertisements includes Admiral appliances, Amoco gasoline, Ballantine Beer, Budweiser Beer, Chevrolet automobiles, Coca-Cola soda, Conoco gasoline, Dr. Pepper soda, Edsel automobiles, Folger's coffee, Ford automobiles, Fritos snacks, Jax Beer, Libby's canned goods, Mobil gas and oil, Mrs. Baird's Bread, Nash automobiles, Northern Tissue, NuGrape soda, Pabst Beer, Schlitz Beer, Sealy mattresses, Shell gasoline, Stratolounger, and Sunshine food products.
The Summary Data Files contain much of the same condensed survey information on advertisement remembrance and product identification found at the front of each survey's folder. The folders in this series contain compiled data sheets of specific data types (remembrance, or identification, etc.) for all (or many) of the surveys conducted in one city. In addition to survey data, there are other documents such as a design master record that presents information in a summary form.
Copy Clues are the monthly reports sent to Brennan's subscribers that interpret survey data, and place it in usable form. This series reflects conclusions drawn from the survey data to communicate specific information on various advertisement attributes. For instance, if multiple designs with dark backgrounds had low remembrance scores, and designs with white backgrounds scored high, Brennan might have brought to his subscriber's attention that white backgrounds make more effective advertising. Did more people remember a product brand if the product was depicted along with a child or without one? Subscribers could receive Copy Clues to answer such questions as well as to receive the survey reports. The final series, Other Surveys and Outdoor Advertising-Related Materials, contains other organizations' surveys, writings, and further information related to outdoor advertising that does not necessarily fit into the previous groupings.
Related collections in the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library include a number of other outdoor advertising collections, such as the Outdoor Advertising Slide Library, the John Paver Papers, the John Browning Papers, the Duplex Advertising Co. Records, the H.E. Fisk Collection of War Effort Mobilization Campaigns, the Outdoor Advertising Association of America Records, the Outdoor Advertising Poster Design Collection, the Garrett Orr Papers, the R.C. Maxwell Company Records, the Howard Scott Papers, and the Strobridge Lithographing Company Advertisements.
Category Descriptions for the Loose Photographs Subseries in the Outdoor Advertising Survey Reports Series
Though well-defined on paper, there is some overlap among these categories for various products, services and businesses. The fluidity of these categories becomes obvious when facing diverse and sometimes vague advertisements. If an initial search in one category is not successful, try a related category.
Amusement & Entertainment
This category contains one advertisement for a live performance by Danny Kaye.
Apparel
This category contains one advertisement for Jantzen Swimsuits and Sun Clothes.
Automotive
This category includes advertisements for the following:
Auto dealers, Auto manufacturers, Auto service, Motor oil, and Tires
This category includes advertisements for items related to cars, except gasoline. Gasoline and gas stations were placed under Transportation & Travel (T & T). Advertisements showing both motor oil and gasoline (and/or car service) were put in the category of the item most prominent. A search for all gas stations should be completed in both this category and T & T.; often an advertisement advertised both car products and gasoline, or just the brand name was presented (such as Texaco, which provides oil, gas, and car service).
Beverages
This category includes advertisements for alcoholic and non-alcoholic beverages including coffee.
Business & Technology
This category includes advertisements for the following:
Banks, Insurance, and Utilities
Many advertisements featuring major appliances are without a brand name--these are probably for a utility company and were placed here.
Consumer Goods & Services
This category includes advertisements for the following:
Appliances, Cemeteries, Funeral services, Gum, Health & Beauty products, Household products, Over-the-counter medicines, Paper products, Tobacco products, and Undertakers
Household products and services were placed here including funeral homes. Cars, motor oil, and car-related products can be found mostly in the Automotive category. Gasoline can be found in the Transportation & Travel category.
Food & Restaurants
This category includes advertisements for the following:
Candy, Food, Ingredients, Prepared foods, Produce, and Restaurants
Gum, pet food, and tobacco products were most often placed in Consumer Goods & Services. Beverages can usually be found in their own Beverages category.
Media and Public Service
This category includes advertising created for a charitable cause or by a non-profit organization, as well as one advertisement for the Yellow Pages. Check this category and Business & Technology for a more comprehensive search.
Retail
This category includes advertisements for the following:
Convenience stores, Department stores, and Grocery stores
Transportation & Travel
This category includes advertisements for the following:
Airlines, Gasoline, and Gasoline stations
Since gas stations but not car service are included in this category, search both this and the Automotive category for an advertisement featuring a company that sold gas and provided auto service.
Market surveys -- United States; Commercial art -- United States; Billboards -- United States; Signs and signboards; Posters -- United States; Posters -- Design; Poster, American -- 20th century -- United States; Advertising, Outdoor -- California -- Los Angeles; Advertising, Outdoor -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Advertising, Outdoor -- Ohio -- Cincinnati; Advertising, Outdoor -- Posters; Billboards -- Design and construction; Advertising -- Research; Advertising -- History; Color photographs; Advertising layout and typography; Advertising -- Posters; Advertising, Outdoor -- United States -- Surveys; Advertising, Outdoor -- Texas -- Houston; Advertising, Outdoor -- Texas -- Dallas; Advertising, Outdoor -- United States -- Statistics; Advertising, Outdoor -- United States; Brennan, John E.; Outdoor Advertising Research Institute; General Media and Copy Research Co; Poster Appraisal Service; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
- Business Correspondence, 1950-1980
  Scope and Contents note
  This small amount of incoming and outgoing correspondence centers on Brennan's business relationships, especially with research consultant Raymond Franzen, who apparently prepared survey samples and evaluated Brennan's methodology. Franzen's 1951 evaluation is included in this series. There is also a small amount of correspondence scattered throughout the Methodology Files.
  - Advertising managers, Letters to, 1951-1952 (Box 1)
  - Franzen, Raymond, Dr., and Sigurd L. Anderson, 1950-1959 (Box 1)
  - Franzen, Raymond, Dr., Evaluation of survey method and sample, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Sinerma and Blackstock, International Outdoor, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
- Methodology Files, 1949-1960s
  This group of materials contains items that reveal Brennan's survey methods, although the coverage is limited. Included are his early thoughts on purpose and research methods, procedures used in planning samples, correspondence with statistician/consultants, as well as training information, basic forms, and maps used in the actual execution of a survey. While most of the collection focuses on Brennan's resulting data and conclusions, these materials provide a closer view of the work needed to compile and produce them. Folders are arranged alphabetically by topic or title of contents.
  See also Legal Size Files.
  - Demographic data form, undated (Box 1)
  - Objectives, Methods, and Significance document, correspondence, and miscellaneous, 1949-1964 and undated (Box 1)
  - On the Masking of Outdoor Advertising Copy in Readership Surveys, undated (Box 1)
  - Product group classification systems, undated (Box 1)
  - Remembrance and ID forms, 1954-1955 (Box 1)
  - Single-city survey vs. national survey sales letter by Brennan, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Survey instructions, 1960s (Box 1)
  - Survey instructions, forms, and maps, 1963-1965 (Box 1)
- Outdoor Advertising Survey Reports, 1947-1980 (bulk 1947-1960s)
  Most of the surveys, which were conducted mainly from 1947 through the mid 1960s, are grouped alphabetically by city. Forty-two different cities were covered, but four cities regularly hosted surveys: Cincinnati (119 surveys), Houston (104 surveys), Los Angeles (209 surveys), and New Haven, Conn. (101 surveys). Dallas also hosted a large number of surveys (76). The two San Jose surveys (late 1970s) were conducted by Brennan's son, John P. Brennan. In this collection, survey usually refers to a particular city and time during which participants were questioned about twenty different ad designs. In the collection, each survey is usually referred to by city, then survey number (i.e. Houston #34, Fresno #3, etc.). Each folder is then devoted to one numbered survey conducted in one city, and includes a title page, a varying number of summary data sheets, a report for each advertisement, and sometimes other information such as data analyzing survey respondents by age or product preferences. Individual advertisement report forms varied over time, but information relating to one ad was usually presented on one or two sheets, including two pasted color photographs of the advertisement, one with the brand name masked or marked out.
  Surveys were conducted differently over the years, but Remembrance and Correct Identification were the two main types of data acquired. Participants were asked if they remembered seeing the advertisement, and with the brand name covered (masked), they were asked if they could identify the product. In some surveys the same interviewee would supply answers to all questions about a particular advertisement, and at times, some interviewees would answer remembrance questions, and a second set would try to identify brands. See the Methodology Files for more information. Besides data on how well the advertisement itself was remembered or if the brand name was correctly identified, the reports provided other information. The size of the poster showing was often presented as well as posting history. Sometimes product misidentifications were recorded, as was relative visibility of the brand, and other statistics.
  Surveys are sometimes referred to as being completed for Outdoor Advertising Incorporated (OAI), the industry's organization created (1931) to advance the concept of outdoor advertising. OAI and other outside organizations such as the Outdoor Advertising Association of America (OAAA), Foster and Kleiser Advertising Co., and Donnelley Advertising contracted with Brennan for surveys, but many evidently were conducted without such an arrangement.
  Advertisements featured in the surveys were created by many different advertising agencies. The agency name was noted on the survey report for each advertisement up until about 1963. Those well-represented in the collection include Barton A. Stebbins Advertising; Batten, Barton, Durstine, & Osborn (BBDO); Benton & Bowles; Calkins & Holden, Carlock, McClinton & Smith; Campbell-Ewald; Cunningham & Walsh; D'Arcy Advertising; Dancer-Fitzgerald-Sample; Foote, Cone, & Belding; Geyer, Newell, & Ganger; Heintz & Co.; Hewitt, Ogilvy, Benson, and Mather; Hixson-Jorgensen; J. Walter Thompson; Johnson & Lewis Advertising; Joseph Katz Co.; Leo Burnett Co.; McCann-Erickson; Midland Advertising; N.W. Ayer & Son; Needham, Louis, & Brorby; Ratcliffe Advertising; Ruthrauff and Ryan; Tracy-Locke; West-Marquis; Wilkinson-Schwietz & Tips; and Young & Rubicam.
  Billboards of many different outdoor advertising companies can usually be identified by the imprint seen in the advertisement photographs. Those companies represented frequently in the collection include Central, Pacific, Foster and Kleiser, General Outdoor Advertising, Houston Poster, Lamar Dean, Middleton, Murphy, Naegele, O'Mealia, Packer, and United.
  After the alphabetical run of survey reports by city, there is a smaller group arranged by product type (e.g. beer, toiletries). The reports within this latter group appear to be copies of reports from the various city surveys pulled together because of the product featured in the advertisement. They do not contain the same introductory/summary information found in the front of most city survey folders. Following this subseries is a group of loose photographs arranged by product or service type.
  Most reports have a small number written or typed beside each photo. These numbers were used to connect photo to report whenever the photo was removed from the paper. This number has been referred to sometimes as the sheet number or design number, and is presumed to be a unique identifier for specific advertisements.
  - Reports Organized by City (alphabetical)
    - Akron #1, 1964 May (Box 1)
    - Albuquerque #1, 1963 June (Box 1)
    - Albuquerque #2, 1963 Dec. (Box 1)
    - Baltimore #1, 1963 July (Box 1)
    - Baltimore #2, 1963 Oct. (Box 1)
    - Baltimore #3, 1964 Jan. (Box 1)
    - Baltimore #4, 1964 Apr. (Box 1)
    - Boston #1, 1963 May (Box 1)
    - Boston #2, 1963 July (Box 2)
    - Boston #3, 1963 Sept. (Box 2)
    - Boston #4, 1963 Nov. (Box 2)
    - Boston #5, 1964 Jan. (Box 2)
    - Boston #6, 1964 Mar. 6 (Box 2)
    - Boston #7, 1964 Mar. 13 (Box 2)
    - Boston #8, 1964 Mar. 20 (Box 2)
    - Boston #9, 1964 Apr. (Box 2)
    - Bridgeport, Conn. #1, 1963 May (Box 2)
    - Bridgeport, Conn. #2, 1963 Nov. (Box 2)
    - Buffalo #1, 1964 May (Box 2)
    - Chicago #1, 1963 May (Box 2)
    - Chicago #2, 1963 July (Box 2)
    - Chicago #3, 1963 Oct. (Box 2)
    - Chicago #4, 1963 Nov. (Box 2)
    - Chicago #5, 1964 Jan. (Box 2)
    - Chicago #6, 1964 Mar. (Box 3)
    - Chicago #7, 1965 Apr. (Box 3)
    - Chicago #8, 1965 July (Box 3)
    - Chicago #9, 1965 Sept. (Box 3)
    - Chicago #10, 1965 Nov. (Box 3)
    - Cincinnati #1, 1948 June (Box 3)
    - Cincinnati #2, 1948 Oct. (Box 3)
    - Cincinnati #3, 1948 Nov. (Box 3)
    - Cincinnati #4, 1948 Dec. (Box 3)
    - Cincinnati #5, 1949 Feb. (Box 3)
    - Cincinnati #6, 1949 Mar. 1 (Box 3)
    - Cincinnati #7, 1949 Mar. 29 (Box 3)
    - Cincinnati #8, 1949 Apr. (Box 3)
    - Cincinnati #9, 1949 May (Box 4)
    - Cincinnati #10, 1949 June (Box 4)
    - Cincinnati #11, 1949 July (Box 4)
    - Cincinnati #12, 1949 Aug. (Box 4)
    - Cincinnati #13, 1949 Sept. (Box 4)
    - Cincinnati #14, 1949 Oct. (Box 4)
    - Cincinnati #15, 1949 Nov. (Box 4)
    - Cincinnati #16, 1949 Dec. (Box 4)
    - Cincinnati #17, 1950 Jan. (Box 4)
    - Cincinnati #18, 1950 Feb. (Box 4)
    - Cincinnati #19, 1950 Mar. (Box 4)
    - Cincinnati #20, 1950 Apr. (Box 4)
    - Cincinnati #21, 1950 May (Box 4)
    - Cincinnati #22, 1950 June (Box 5)
    - Cincinnati #23, 1950 July (Box 5)
    - Cincinnati #24, 1950 Aug. (Box 5)
    - Cincinnati #25, 1950 Sept. (Box 5)
    - Cincinnati #26, 1950 Oct. (Box 5)
    - Cincinnati #27, 1950 Nov. (Box 5)
    - Cincinnati #28, 1950 Dec. (Box 5)
    - Cincinnati #29, 1951 Jan. (Box 5)
    - Cincinnati #30, 1951 Feb. (Box 5)
    - Cincinnati #31, 1951 Mar. (Box 5)
    - Cincinnati #32, 1951 Apr. (Box 5)
    - Cincinnati #33, 1951 May (Box 5)
    - Cincinnati #34, 1951 June (Box 6)
    - Cincinnati #35, 1951 July (Box 6)
    - Cincinnati #36, 1951 Aug. (Box 6)
    - Cincinnati #37, 1951 Sept. (Box 6)
    - Cincinnati #38, 1951 Oct. (Box 6)
    - Cincinnati #39, 1951 Nov. (Box 6)
    - Cincinnati #40, 1951 Dec. (Box 6)
    - Cincinnati #41, 1952 Jan. (Box 6)
    - Cincinnati #42, 1952 Feb. (Box 6)
    - Cincinnati #43, 1952 Mar. (Box 6)
    - Cincinnati #44, 1952 Apr. (Box 6)
    - Cincinnati #45, 1952 May (Box 6)
    - Cincinnati #46, 1952 June (Box 7)
    - Cincinnati #47, 1952 July (Box 7)
    - Cincinnati #48, 1952 Aug. (Box 7)
    - Cincinnati #49, 1952 Sept. (Box 7)
    - Cincinnati #50, 1952 Oct. (Box 7)
    - Cincinnati #51, 1952 Nov. (Box 7)
    - Cincinnati #52, 1952 Dec. (Box 7)
    - Cincinnati #53, 1953 Jan. (Box 7)
    - Cincinnati #54, 1953 Feb. (Box 7)
    - Cincinnati #55, 1953 Mar. (Box 7)
    - Cincinnati #56, 1953 Apr. (Box 7)
    - Cincinnati #57, 1953 May (Box 8)
    - Cincinnati #58, 1953 June (Box 8)
    - Cincinnati #59, 1953 July (Box 8)
    - Cincinnati #60, 1953 Aug. (Box 8)
    - Cincinnati #61, 1953 Sept. (Box 8)
    - Cincinnati #62, 1953 Oct. (Box 8)
    - Cincinnati #63, 1953 Nov. (Box 8)
    - Cincinnati #64, 1953 Dec. (Box 8)
    - Cincinnati #65, 1954 Jan. (Box 8)
    - Cincinnati #66, 1954 Mar. 1 (Box 8)
    - Cincinnati #67, 1954 Mar. 29 (Box 8)
    - Cincinnati #68, 1954 Apr. (Box 8)
    - Cincinnati #69, 1954 May (Box 8)
    - Cincinnati #70, 1954 June (Box 9)
    - Cincinnati #71, 1954 July (Box 9)
    - Cincinnati #72, 1954 Aug. (Box 9)
    - Cincinnati #73, 1954 Sept. (Box 9)
    - Cincinnati #74, 1954 Oct. (Box 9)
    - Cincinnati #75, 1954 Nov. (Box 9)
    - Cincinnati #76, 1954 Dec. (Box 9)
    - Cincinnati #77, 1955 Jan. (Box 9)
    - Cincinnati #78, 1955 Feb. (Box 9)
    - Cincinnati #79, 1955 Mar. (Box 9)
    - Cincinnati #80, 1955 Apr. (Box 9)
    - Cincinnati #81, 1955 May (Box 10)
    - Cincinnati #82, 1955 June (Box 10)